Good day everyone.
This is Gnome's Well, a 2D game where
you play as a gnome searching for treasure
in a well while dodging traps along the
way.
The game is simple.
You control the length of the rope as
it goes up and down the well while
tilting the phone to move the gnome left
and right.
So I will show you a quick demo
in this activity.
So here's the game.
So now we go into the overview of
architecture and the main components.
So for the architecture, Gnome's well core architecture
uses Unity's 2D physics engine as its foundation
allowing for dynamic movement of the gnome and
its chain link rope system.
The player interaction is managed by a dual
system input system.
Device tilt for horizontal movement and on-screen
buttons for rope length.
The in-game elements including the objective interactions,
win-loss conditions, and camera behavior are handled
by a central game manager.
So now we go into the main components.
The first component is the gnome.
The player character is a ragdoll composed of
multiple rigid bodies connected by joints, allowing for
a realistic physical movement and reactions to collisions.
Next is the rope.
A dynamic system of interconnected rigid bodies and
joints.
Its length can be increased or decreased by
the player influencing the gnome's descent and movement.
Next is the input system.
The player control involves tilting the device to
move the gnome left and right and using
on-screen up and down buttons to adjust
the rope's length.
Next is the collision detection.
Touching a trap leads to the gnome's death
which prompts a new gnome to appear.
Touching treasure updates the gnome's sprites to show
it holding the treasure.
Touching the well's top while holding a treasure
signifies the player's win.
Next is the camera.
The camera follows the gnome as it moves
down the well.
But it's restricted by set top and bottom
boundaries so player don't see empty space outside
the game area.
Lastly, the game manager.
A central object which orchestrates the overall game
flow.
Responsible for managing game states, creating new gnomes,
coordinating interactions with traps and treasures.
Handling menus and connecting other systems like the
rope and camera to the current gnome.
Now we go to the step-by-step
coding highlights.
So first we go to the GameManager.
This is the script responsible for the game
states, gnome creation, reset, win-loss conditions and
UI visibility.
Next is the Rope.
This script manages dynamic rope generation, extension, retraction
and visual rendering based on physics.
Next is the Gnome.
This handles the gnome's individual state.
For example, holding treasure or dead.
Damage responses and initiate death effects.
So next is the InputManager.
Processes device tilt for sideways movement and manages
rope lengthening or shortening flags from UI buttons.
Next is the CameraFollow.
This keeps the camera's vertical position, tracking the
gnome within defined upper and lower boundaries of
the well.
And lastly, the SignalOnTouch.
A generic script used by interactive objects like
traps, treasures and exit to detect player collisions
and trigger specific unit events.
For example, the spike traps uses SignalOnTouch
to make sure the gnome dies when
it touches or collides with it.
Next we go to the logic breakdown.
First is the rope physics.
The rope is dynamically generated during runtime as
a chain of game objects, each provided with
a rigid 2D and a spring joint 2D
components.
These joints link the rope segments together with
the top anchored to the well and the
bottom connected to the gnome's leg rope.
The length is adjusted with the update method
of the rope script.
This method changes the spring joint 2D distance
of the top segment and adds or removes
segments based on the player's input through on
-screen buttons.
A line renderer component is updated each frame
to visually represent the rope.
Next is collision.
Collision is managed by the SignalOnTouch.cs
which is attached to traps, treasures and
the exit to detect contact with the gnome.
When triggered, the script uses a pre-configured
unit event that the game manager responds to.
For traps, this calls trapTouch or fireTrapTouch, resulting
in the gnome's death and respawn.
For treasures, it calls treasureCollected, which sets gnome
.holdingTreasure equals true, and updates gnome's arm sprite
by the sprite swapper.
At the exit, exitReach is called, which checks
the holding treasure flag to determine if the
player has achieved a win condition.
Next is scoring or win condition.
Scoring is based on treasureCollection, which also serves
as the player's primary goal.
The game is won when the gnome reaches
the exit at the top of the well,
while the holding treasure flag is true.
This condition is evaluated by the game manager
.exitReach method, which if met, triggers the win
state and displays the "You win" UI.
And lastly, the UI or the User Interface.
The UI includes up and down buttons that
adjust the rope lengths using event triggers, menu
screens for gameplay and navigations, and an invincibility
toggle linked to the game manager.
The game manager controls the menus are active
based on game state, while event triggers handles
continuous button input, and the canvas scaler keeps
the layout consistent across devices.
Now we go to the assets and folder
structure.
The assets folder contains important subfolders for organizing
game assets.
First, we go to the Scripts.
This folder contains all the C# code
for the game.
Next, we go to the Sounds.
This folder contains both music and sound effects.
Next, we go to the Sprites.
This folder contains all the sprite images, which
are further organized into subfolders.
Next is the Gnome.
This folder contains prefabs for the gnome character,
as well as related objects like rope and
the particle effects.
Next, we go to the Level.
This folder contains prefabs for the level itself,
including the background, walls, decorative objects, and traps.
Lastly, we go to the App Resources.
This folder contains resources used by the entire
applications, such as its icon and splash screen.
Now we go to the build and run
instructions.
To test the game, install Unity Remote.
Download the Unity Remote app from your device's
app store.
Number two, connect device.
Launch Unity Remote on your phone and connect
your phone to your computer using a USB
cable.
Number three, go to configure Unity Editor.
In the Unity Editor, open the edit menu
and choose project settings and then go to
editor.
In the inspector, change the device settings to
your phone from none to your any Android
device.
Then next and lastly, launch the game in
editor.
Click the play button in the Unity Editor.
The game will appear on the connected device
and you can interact with it as if
it were installed.
Now we go to the known issues and
improvement.
For the known issues, the first is Unity
Remote rotation.
If the phone is rotated too far while
using Unity Remote, it may switch to landscape
mode and stretching the picture.
The document suggests turning on the device's rotation
lock to prevent this.
Next is the compiler errors.
When initially adding the Gnome script, compiler errors
related to remove after delay are expected as
the class is defined later.
The tutorials provided code for GameManager.cs and
Singleton.cs scripts utilize the deprecated Unity functions
FindObjectOfType and FindObjectsOfType.
The engine recommends replacing this with their more
efficient modern equivalents FindFirstObjectByType and FindObjectsByType.
And last for the known issues, since Unity
Remote does not run the game natively, instead,
it streams a heavily compressed video feed from
the editor to the mobile device.
The compression can potentially cause significant input lag
and visual degradation, which may not provide an
accurate representation of the final game.
And for our possible improvements, the possible improvements
would be adding a ghost sprite that appears
when the gnome dies, introducing new traps like
swinging blades and flamethrowers, creating more levels and
enhancing visuals with particle effects around the treasures
and walls.
A burning effect could also be implemented as
an extra challenge.
So that concludes our presentation.
Before I will end this video, I would
like to introduce myself and my group members.
I am Jan Ellisson Sebastian, their leader, and
my group members are Ver Raquepo and
Gano Spencer Chumilang.
They're responsible for developing and coding this project.
And lastly, here's the link to our github
repository.
So that's it and thank you for watching.